Kia ora. Can I check you can hear and see me?
Good morning, Lizzie. Very good to have you here.
I'm Sam Athfield, chair of the Health Committee. We have members around the table.
Welcome. It's very nice to have the opportunity to hear from you.
We have you here for 10 minutes. If you want to leave us time for questions,
you may. We have read your written
submission.
We will hand that time over to you now. Thank you.
Okay. Thank you.
Tena koutou, tena koutou, tena koutou katoa.
Thank you for the opportunity to talk with you today.
I'm Lizzie Carey. I'm a qualified clinical prosthetist orthotist.
I provide prosthetic limbs for people living with limb difference or amputation,
helping them maintain mobility, independence, employment, and participation in
community life. I trained in the UK and moved to New Zealand in
2016 in response to a recognized skills shortage.
New Zealand has no domestic degree program for our profession, so we depend heavily
on clinicians who have trained overseas.
My experience includes working in the NHS, then NZALS, now known as Peki
Wāhanga,
and I have also worked for one of the largest global prosthetic manufacturers
training clinicians across Australia and New Zealand, as well as delivering
training programs across Africa, South America, and Sri Lanka to improve access to
quality prosthetic care. There is a global shortage of prosthetist
orthotists, and due to New Zealand's lower wages and limited employer options, New
Zealand is struggling to obtain and maintain staffing levels required.
I've seen what New Zealand's prosthetic sector can achieve.
However, I've also seen many skilled clinicians leave, patients disengage from
care, and independent providers prevented from contributing fully because
publicly funded prosthetic care remains concentrated with one provider, Peki
Wāhanga.
Peki Wāhanga is a Crown entity, and I want to acknowledge that they provide
valuable and essential services to New Zealanders and have skilled clinicians.
I'm not asking for Peki Wāhanga to be dismantled.
The concern is the structure around it.
Since the National Artificial Limb Service, now known as Peki Wāhanga, developed as
post-World War service for veterans, publicly funded prosthetic care has been
delivered predominantly through a single-provider model.
There was a short period in the '90s when another provider held a regional
contract. This was followed by a Health and Disability Commissioner's report in
2000 that stated that patients in that region were only offered a choice
between providers for approximately five months before contracts were changed to
sole provider national contracts.
Meaningful patient choice has otherwise been largely absent for the past 80 years.
No single provider, particularly a Crown entity, that is also a service provider
should be the only accessible funded option for almost every amputee.
Prosthetic care is not a single episode of care.
It's a lifelong clinical relationship.
Throughout the amputee's lifetime, their residual limb changes shape and size and
may experience complications such as painful neuromas,
and bespoke prosthetics need to be replaced to match their current limb shape to
prevent injury, pain, and wounds.
Patients and their whānau have experienced a life-changing event that leaves them
reliant on prosthetic care providers.
When one organization controls almost every stage of that funded
stage of that relationship, the patient is placed in a uniquely
dependent position.
In most areas of healthcare, if trust breaks down or a person feels their needs are
not being met, they can seek another qualified clinician, and this is currently
possible in physiotherapy and podiatry.
For most New Zealand amputees, that ordinary safeguard is not available.
To paint the picture, I think it's important to hear the real-life experiences.
One of our patients, Jess Quinn, has given explicit consent to share her story with
you today. Jess had an amputation following cancer as a child,
and she was able to get really active as a young adult,
jogging and even competing on "Dancing with the Stars." Unfortunately, she began
experiencing swelling in her limb, which was unable to be resolved with the only
prosthetic provider in New Zealand, and after two and a half years of these issues
and pain, she privately self-funded a prosthesis to be made in America,
which resolved these issues. However, after COVID, regular traveling to the US
wasn't feasible, and over the next three years, multiple unsuccessful
attempts to refit the prosthesis by Peki Wāhanga resulted in chronic pressure
sores.
She was referred to have surgery.
Jess requested a second opinion from myself, and within three weeks of receiving
the prosthetic I made for her, the pressure sores had completely healed, and the
surgery was avoided. In her words, "I could have gone through a pretty risky
surgery, in a sense I have no idea of what could have caused further
complications. I was seeing every specialist under the sun.
I think it just shows how desperate I got.
I spent a long time thinking this part of my life was over, the part where I could
move, work out, feel strong, and I can now." There are many similar stories to
her case of people being impacted by pain and lack of resolution, leading them to
avoid returning to the only funded service provider, and some resorting to
abandoned prosthetic use. I'm not suggesting that every complex fitting
or clinical disagreement represents a failure. Prosthetic care is complex.
Residual limbs change, components sometimes fail, and achieving a successful fit
can require several attempts or approaches.
The complexity clearly points to the need for patients to have alternative options
and for long-term support with a clinician who fits them best to be
funded. Patients should have autonomy to choose their provider.
Currently, the only pathway available to receiving a second opinion with a
prosthetist is through arduous complaints process, which is only available to
some ACC patients and is not guaranteed.
Health-funded patients have to self-fund to see another provider.
A complaints process is important, but it cannot substitute for
provider choice. A patient shouldn't have to prove negligence or misconduct
before being allowed to receive care from another appropriately qualified
clinician.
Official Information Act requests from September 2025 showed that only 16 amputees
across the past five years were approved to see an alternative
provider in New Zealand.
There are close to 5,000 prosthetic users in New Zealand, and that equates to
0.3% of users, and only 11 patients were fully funded.
This is not freedom of choice. This is exceptional circumstances.
We face several connected issues in this industry: disparity in patient funding
between ACC and Health New Zealand patients, absence of meaningful choice of
provider or clinician, and high staff turnover and limited employment options.
A sustainable workforce requires multiple employers, viable independent practice,
opportunities for clinical specialization and professional development available
across the profession, not just concentrated within one organization.
And I want to be clear, I'm not asking for deregulation of the industry.
Today, I'm asking the committee to recommend three practical actions.
Firstly, a funded patient choice pathway, under which the appropriately qualified
and independently accredited providers can deliver prosthetic care within national
standards. Public funding should follow the patient and their assessed clinical
needs to the accredited provider of their choice, rather than automatically
attaching that person to one institution for life.
Secondly, an immediate and transparent alternative provider pathway when the
relationship has broken down, the patient has unresolved fit, safety, or functional
concerns, a second clinical opinion is justified, or they do not consent to
returning to a previous provider.
And thirdly, a national consistent outcome reporting to an independent body
that covers all providers and includes both patient-reported outcomes and
functional outcome measures, falls and adverse events, complaints, transfers, and
people disengaging from services. We can provide more details after this meeting.
In closing, this is about building a wider, more resilient, and accountable system
in which patients have a meaningful alternative.
Giving amputees meaningful provider choice would protect their autonomy, strengthen
clinical accountability, retain skilled clinicians in New Zealand, and help public
funding achieve better long-term outcomes.
And currently, we don't have the framework for prosthetists to develop their
careers, and the current system makes it difficult for independent practitioners,
like myself, to run their own sustainable business.
I'd like to note that the president of NZOPA, our association, and some amputees
have offered to be present in this call if you have questions that are more
relevant to them.
Lizzie, thank you very much for your submission today.
The main message we're getting is that there's no practical
accessible funding provider choice, leading to poorer outcomes
for New Zealanders. And you've listed three
recommendations there. I've seen Ayesha Vero has her hand up. Dr. Vero.
Thank you, Lizzie, for a very clear and succinct presentation.
I really appreciate it.
The point you make about
a patient's right to a second opinion is a good one.
It's in the Code of Patient Rights.
Can you explain,
normally where I've seen that right given effect too, it's
where, in my experiences in hospitals,
the relationship breaks down between one specialist
and the patient, and there's another specialist
employed in the hospital who's able to
offer the second opinion. Can you explain why that
is not possible through
the model that we have within the
artificial limb center?
Sorry, you cut out there slightly on the-
Well, within the provider that we have, why
can't second opinions from within the provider that we have
address the issue of the patient right to a
second opinion?
I hear you. And many patients have resorted to that and been bounced around the
country to different centers trying to find a clinician
that can solve their challenges and think outside the box of what's
been happening for them.
But unfortunately, that has often
not succeeded. It does work for some people, and they have to travel quite
lengthy distances, so I'm not disregarding that it does work for some people.
But I think maybe that would be
more appropriate to explain
the patient's experience of that.
So there are multiple clinicians in the country in that one company,
but one company has one service provision model.
And if you wanted to go see a physio, you could go to a different physio, or if you
wanted a second opinion from a surgeon, it doesn't have to be in the same hospital
for them to be valid. They're still skilled clinicians.
Well, it is for it to be state-funded.
That is the case, that your second opinion from within the public
health system would usually be from that same provider.
Because what your answer suggests to me is
that
if patients aren't getting their issue resolved by a second opinion
from
within the provider, then are you suggesting there's an
issue about
clinical standards and competence within that organization?
I think there's a multi-factor issue here.
Part of the issues is people being time poor and having
a much larger caseload than previous, like maybe about eight, 10 years
ago. There's many more amputees coming through the system.
There's a number of factors
involved in this issue, and I think Hendrik's got his hand up to talk
on that association, because I don't think this should be a conversation about
how they're not
doing their work. I don't want to be...
Yeah.
Thank you, Lizzie. We're over time, but I noticed Hendrik and
Ian have their hands up. So we'll go Hendrik quickly and then to Ian as well.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for the opportunity.
Just to give a little bit of context for a prosthetic user, it's not
a one-off transaction, like where you're sitting at a hospital and you see a
specialist and you don't get along with them, they can get another one from the
hospital and get it done. It's a long-term
thing. It's not, "I'm going to see my prosthetist today, and then I'm not going to
see them again." It's going to be a regular, often, relationship
that you build with a person. If you don't get along with this person,
your prosthetic care is going to suffer.
Thank you, Hendrik. Ian.
You're on mute, sorry.
Good morning. Thank you for the opportunity.
I'm a- Double above knee amputee of 15 years.
I have very high-tech legs that there's only one person in the
country who knows how to actually operate them and actually make
me be able to walk. There's nobody at the Artificial Limb Service who
has got the intellect on the legs. They know how
to make legs, but they don't have the intellect to actually
set the legs up.
Lizzy Carey is the only person who can do that.
And so I'm telling you right now that if Lizzy has to go,
my opportunity to walk, due to my physiology, I'm not going to have that
opportunity, because I will not go back to the Artificial Limb Service
because I'm not going to sit there for six hours at a time waiting for
somebody to actually try and find out how to actually do the legs.
I've worked for the Artificial Limb Service as a life coach.
I know how busy they are. They do not have time
to put into a person like myself that's very high needs with
high-tech legs.
That's all I can say is-
Thank you, Ian
... they don't have the time to actually upskill themselves.
Thank you, Ian.
We are over time, but I want to give Naomi the opportunity to
start, and then we will close. Naomi.
So I just wanted to just bring it back to your question a bit more.
Why can't we just see someone else within the same system?
I did. So I changed
therapists multiple times following the more
experienced therapists. But like Lizzy said,
generally when they are experienced, we lose them.
Their workload is huge. Nothing against Piki Waihanga therapists,
but it's weeks before you can get in.
Even communication can be a real problem, just because they are too busy.
And so for anyone who has a slightly more difficult limb,
we end up chasing the experience. So going from center to center.
I'm a physio, so if you were coming to see me and you weren't happy with what
I was doing or I was too busy, you would go to another center, which would still
be funded. So to your point that the
funding stays within the same one,
different industries are different with that.
So I really think that we should be allowed to see a different
therapist,
covered, despite the fact it's not within the same company.
Thank you, Naomi. And thank you everyone for your participation.
Lizzy, for all the work that you do.
Good to have you here this morning. Kia ora.
Thank you.
Yeah.
We'll move back to private, please.